A Finding Aid to the Patti Warashina Papers, circa 1900-1991, bulk 1970-1989, in the Archives of American Art AAA.warapatt
Archives of American Art
Patti Warashina papers
bulk 1970-1989
circa 1900-1991
AAA.warapatt
Archives of American Art
4.8 Linear feet
The papers of ceramicist and sculptor Patti Warashina (b. 1940) date from circa 1900 and 1957 through 1991, bulk 1970-1989. The collection consists of 4.8 linear feet of correspondence and printed material reflecting the many ceramic and craft exhibitions and other projects Warashina participated in throughout the United States, and her associations with other ceramicists. Also included are biographical documents, writings, art works, several photographs, and a video.
Patti Warashina
Biographical Note
Ceramicist and sculptor Patti Warashina was born in 1940 as Masae Patricia Warashina in Spokane, Washington to third generation Japanese emigrants. She received her undergraduate degree from the University of Washington, Seattle, where she studied with sculptors Robert Sperry, Harold Myers, Rudy Autio, Shoji Hamada, Shinsaku Hamada, and Ruth Penington. She received her first solo exhibition in 1962 at the Phoenix Art Gallery in Seattle the same year she graduated with an M.F.A. from the University of Washington. Warashina later married fellow student Fred Bauer and from 1964 to 1970 exhibited as Patti Bauer.
Influences in Warashina's art include California funk and sculptural ceramics. Her work is best known for its whimsical themes expressed through low-fire highly colored figurative images. Together with fellow artists Robert Sperry, Howard Kottler and Fred Bauer, she brought national recognition to the department of ceramics at the University of Washington's School of Art beginning in the 1980s.
Patti Warashina is a recipient of several awards for achievements in the field of crafts, most recently the Twining Humber Award granted by Seattle's Artists Trust in 2002. She received the Governor's Award of Special Commendation for the Arts in 1980 in addition to grants from the National Endowment for the Arts in both 1975 and 1986. In 1978, Warashina was awarded a World Craft Council Travel Grant which allowed her to conduct research on the ceramic arts process in Japan, Hong Kong, Singapore, Thailand, Bali and the Philippines. Warashina's teaching career spans over 30 years and includes positions at the University of Wisconsin, Eastern Michigan University, and at her alma mater where she has taught for over 25 years. Her work is featured in several museum collections in both the U.S. and abroad including the American Craft Museum in New York, the Seattle Art Museum and Henry Art Gallery, the Smithsonian American Art Museum's Renwick Gallery (Washington, DC), the Art Gallery of Western Australia, and the Ichon World Ceramic Center in Korea. Since her marriage to ceramicist Robert Sperry in 1976, she has used Patti Warashina as her professional name. Patti Warashina is a resident of Seattle, Washington.
Scope and Content Note
The Patti Warashina papers measure 4.8 linear feet and date from circa 1900 and 1957 through 1991 (bulk 1970-1989). The collection documents the artistic and teaching career of Seattle-based sculptor and ceramicist Patti Warashina predominantly through correspondence and printed material reflecting the many ceramic and craft exhibitions and other projects Warashina participated in throughout the United States, and her associations with other ceramicists. Also included are biographical documents, writings, art works, several photographs, and a video.
Biographical material includes family trees, diplomas, awards, and documents relating to Warashina's family Japanese internment during WWII. Correspondence, 1968-1991, relating to exhibitions and other projects, is with galleries, museums, purchasers, publishers, and others, among them the Lee Nordness Gallery (N.Y.), Morgan Gallery (Kansas City), and Theo Portney Gallery (Seattle). Additional correspondence files contain letters received, 1977-1990, many addressed to Warashina and her husband Bob (Robert Sperry), from friends, colleagues, former students and family members, including Nancy Carmen, Anne Currier, Deborah Horrell, Matthew Kangas, Howard Kottler, Marvin Lipofsky, Michael Lucero, and others.
Ten photographs, circa 1900-1944, are portraits of Warashina's relatives and family, and several snapshots, circa 1970s, are of former students and works of art. Printed material, 1961-1990, includes newspaper and magazine clippings, programs, journals, newsletters, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and workshop announcements for Warashina's various sculpture and ceramic lectures. Writings include both published and unpublished works by Warashina, including an artist's statement for a possible lecture at the 1986 conference of the National Council on Education for the Ceramic Arts (NCECA). Also found here are handwritten notes on a panel discussion titled Cultural and Racial Heritage: Sources and Imagery in which Warashina was a participant along with artists Aminah Brenda Lynn Robinson, María Brito Avellana, and Indira Johnson. Art work consists of blue line drawings for her sculpture "Red Earth," 1986 as well as a pen and ink sketch of Warashina by an unidentified artist. A videocassette, 1987, is of the television program "The Big A: Different Ways of Seeing", in which Warashina appears briefly.
Arrangement
The Patti Warashina papers are arranged as seven series based primarily on type of material. The correspondence in Series 2 is arranged chronologically for exhibitions and projects and general letters received. Additional letters received are arranged by name of author.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1974-1991, undated (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1957, 1967-1991, undated (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1900- circa 1959, 1971, undated (Box 3; 3 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1961-1990, undated (Boxes 3-6, OV 7; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 5: Writings and Notes, 1984, 1986, 1989, undated (Box 6; 4 folders)
Series 6: Artwork, 1986, undated (Box 6; 2 folders)
Series 7: Miscellany, 1987, undated (Box 6; 2 folders)
Provenance
The Patti Warashina papers were donated by the artist to the Archives of American Art in 1991.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Currier, Anne, 1950-; Kottler, Howard, 1930-1989; Lee Nordness Galleries; Lipofsky, Marvin, 1938-; Lucero, Michael, 1953-; Sperry, Robert, 1927-1998; Asian American women artists; Ceramicists--Washington (State)--Seattle; Japanese American families--Photographs; Japanese American sculptors; Photographs; Sculptors--Washington (State)--Seattle; Video recordings; Women artists--Washington (State)--Seattle; Women sculptors--Washington (State)--Seattle
- Biographical Material, 1974-1991, undated; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series houses certificates of awards, diplomas, and a family history and genealogy of the Warshina family with notations written in Japanese.
  - Biographical Material, 1974-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
- Correspondence, 1957, 1967-1991, undated; Series 2; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Exhibition correspondence relating to the many ceramic and craft exhibitions and art projects in which Warashina participated throughout the United States and abroad. Letters Received discuss personal and professional matters and are addressed both to Warashina and her husband Robert (Bob) Sperry. Exhibition Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year. Letters Received are arranged in alphabetical order by name of correspondent except for "Letters Received, General," which are arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, Exhibitions and Projects, 1957, 1967-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4-24)
  - Correspondence, Exhibitions and Projects, 1985-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
  - Letters Received, General, 1957, 1977-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-32)
  - Letters Received, Bitar, Helen, 1976-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters Received, Carman, Nancy, 1978-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters Received, Currier, Anne, 1975-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Family, 1979-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Former Students (A-Y), circa 1970-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Horrell, Deborah, 1980-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Kangas, Matthew, 1980-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Kottler, Howard, 1980-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lipofsky, Marvin, 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lucero, Michael, 1979-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Nordness, Lee, 1982-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Schwartz, Judy, 1980-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Tielman, Betsy, 1983-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Photographs, circa 1900 - circa 1959, 1971, undated; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 3
  - Photographs, circa 1900 - circa 1959, 1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
- Printed Material, 1961-1990, undated; Series 4; 2 Linear feet Boxes 3-6, OV 7
  This series houses English and Japanese exhibition announcements and catalogs for group and solo shows, newspaper and magazine clippings, programs, art journals, and newsletters. Also found are announcements for publications, workshop announcements for several of Warashina's lectures on sculpture and ceramics, and a 1977 catalog for the University of Washington's School of Art located in Seattle. The catalog includes reproductions of artwork and biographical information on faculty members Jacob Lawrence, Norman Lundin, Alden Mason, Boyer Gonzales, Michael Spafford, Robert Sperry, and Patti Warashina. The series also includes the book, Clay's the Way by Gene Kleinsmith, about various clay techniques used in ceramics.
  - Advertisements for Publications, 1986-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1970-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 21-27)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Posters, 1971-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
    See also OV 7.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1965-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-16)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Journals and Newsletters, 1976-1989, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Kleinsmith, Gene, Clay's the Way, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 6-12)
  - Magazine Clippings, 1965, 1971-1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
  - Programs and Calendars of Events, 1971-1989, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - University of Washington's School of Art Catalog, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Workshop Announcements, 1975-1989, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1965, 1981-1990, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oversize Exhibition Announcements, Posters, undated (Box OV 7)
  - Oversize Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box OV 7)
- Writings and Notes, 1984, 1986, 1989, undated; Series 5; 4 Folders Box 6
  This series includes artist statements by Warashina, undated notes on a panel discussion titled "Cultural and Racial Heritage: Sources and Imagery" and notes regarding exhibition schedules. Also found is a 1984 thesis paper written by Rebecca Sue Bleicher Bloom, "Northwest Women Artists: Images and Ideas" as well as other miscellaneous written material.
  - Artist Statements by Patti Warashina, 1986, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Handwritten notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Thesis by Rebecca Sue Bleicher Bloom and Other Unpublished Writings, 1984, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Artwork, 1986, undated; Series 6; 2 Folders Box 6
  - Designs for Warashina's Sculpture, Red Earth, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Original Artwork, Pen and Ink Sketch, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Miscellany, 1987, undated; Series 7; 2 Folders Box 6
  Ephemera and a video cassette and accompanying teacher's kit for the program, The Big A: Different Ways of Seeing in which Warashina appears briefly.
  - Ephemera, Lapel Button, "Patti Warashina", undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Video and Teacher's Art Kit, The Big A: Different Ways of Seeing, 1987; 1 Videocassettes (Box 6, Folder 12)